<chapter title="Gradient boosting performs gradient descent"
	 author={[Terence Parr](http://parrt.cs.usfca.edu) and [Jeremy Howard](http://www.fast.ai/about/#jeremy)}>

\todo{can't proof that it converges or is correct... it's just a way to show that it can work with any differentiable loss function or equivalently direction vector}

Prince says this is an important distinction for him to understand when I said it: chasing the residual vector chases the mean squared error versus chasing sign vector which does not. The gradient of L2 is the residual vector and we chase gradient in gradient descent.

So far we've looked at GBMs that use two different direction vectors, the residual vector ([Gradient boosting: Distance to target](L2-loss.htm)) and the sign vector ([Gradient boosting: Heading in the right direction](L1-loss.htm)). It's natural to ask whether there are other direction vectors we can use and what effect they have on the final $F_M(X)$ predictions.  Your intuition probably told you that nudging the intermediate $\hat{\vec y}$ prediction towards target $\vec y$ gradually improves model performance, but would $\hat{\vec y}$ ever stop if we kept increasing $M$? If so, where would it stop? Is there something special or interesting about the sequence of vectors that $\hat{\vec y}$ passes through? Moreover, training a model on observations ($\vec x$, $y$) is a matter of finding a function, $F(\vec x)$, that optimizes some cost or loss function indicating how well $F$ performs. (The procedure is to tweak model $F$'s parameters until we minimize the loss function.) What loss function is a GBM optimizing and what is the relationship with the choice of direction vector?

To answer these questions, we're going to employ a mathematician's favorite trick: showing how our current problem is just a flavor of another well-known problem for which we have lots of useful results. Specifically, this article shows how gradient boosting machines perform an optimization technique from numerical methods called [gradient or steepest descent](https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gradient_descent). We'll see that a GBM training weak leaners on residual vectors optimizes the mean squared error (MSE), the $L_2$ loss, between the true target $\vec y$ and the intermediate predictions, $\hat{\vec y} = F_m(X)$. A GBM that trains weak learners on sign vectors optimizes the mean absolute error (MAE), the $L_1$ loss. 

Before jumping into the mathematics, let's make some observations about the behavior of our gradient boosting machines based on the examples from the previous two articles.
 
<section title="Comparing drop in MSE when chasing residual vs sign vectors">
 
Let's revisit the $\hat y = F_m(\vec x)$ intermediate model predictions for both the weak learners trained on residual vectors and those trained on sign vectors.  We can empirically verify that training $\Delta_m$ weak models on the residual vector drops the MSE loss dramatically faster than training $\Delta_m$ on the sign vector. Here is the data pulled from the first article with the MSE and MAE tacked on:

<latex>
{\small
\setlength{\tabcolsep}{0.5em}
\begin{tabular}[t]{rrrrrrr}
\multicolumn{7}{c}{$\Delta_m$ {\bf trained on residual vector} $\vec y - \hat{\vec y}$}\\
&$\vec x~~~$ & $\vec y~~~$ & \multicolumn{4}{c}{...$~\hat{\vec y}$~...}\vspace{-1mm}\\
&{\bf SqFeet} & {\bf Rent} & $F_0(\vec x)$ & $F_1(\vec x)$ & $F_2(\vec x)$ & $F_3(\vec x)$\\
\hline
& 750 & 1160 & 1418 & 1272 & 1180 & 1195 \\
& 800 & 1200 & 1418 & 1272 & 1180 & 1195 \\
& 850 & 1280 & 1418 & 1272 & 1334 & 1349 \\
& 900 & 1450 & 1418 & 1272 & 1334 & 1349 \\
& 950 & 2000 & 1418 & 2000 & 2061 & 2000 \\
\hline
\vspace{-4mm}\\
{\bf MSE}&\multicolumn{2}{l}{$\frac{1}{N}\sum_i^N(y_i-F_m(\vec x_i))^2$} & 94576 & 9895 & 4190.8 & 3240.1\\
{\bf MAE}&\multicolumn{2}{l}{$\frac{1}{N}\sum_i^N|y_i-F_m(\vec x_i)|$} & 246 & 74 & 54 & 42
\end{tabular}
}
</latex>

and here is the data pulled from the second article with the MSE and MAE tacked on:

<latex>
{\small
\setlength{\tabcolsep}{0.5em}
\begin{tabular}[t]{rrrrrrr}
\multicolumn{7}{c}{$\Delta_m$ {\bf trained on sign vector} $sign(\vec y - \hat{\vec y})$}\\
&$\vec x~~~$ & $\vec y~~~$ & \multicolumn{4}{c}{...$~\hat{\vec y}$~...}\vspace{-1mm}\\
& {\small\bf SqFeet} & {\bf Rent} & $F_0(\vec x)$ & $F_1(\vec x)$ & $F_2(\vec x)$ & $F_3(\vec x)$\\
\hline
& 750 & 1160 & 1280 & 1180 & 1160 & 1155 \\
& 800 & 1200 & 1280 & 1180 & 1190 & 1185 \\
& 850 & 1280 & 1280 & 1450 & 1460 & 1455 \\
& 900 & 1450 & 1280 & 1450 & 1460 & 1455 \\
& 950 & 2000 & 1280 & 1450 & 1460 & 2000 \\
\hline
\vspace{-4mm}\\
{\bf MSE}&\multicolumn{2}{l}{$\frac{1}{N}\sum_i^N(y_i-F_m(\vec x_i))^2$} & 113620 & 66440 & 64840 & 6180\\
{\bf MAE}&\multicolumn{2}{l}{$\frac{1}{N}\sum_i^N|y_i-F_m(\vec x_i)|$} & 218 & 152 & 148 & 40 \\
\end{tabular}
}
</latex>

There are a number of interesting things going on here. First, recall that we used the average for the $f_0$ model in the first article and the median in the second article because the average minimizes the MSE and the median minimizes the MAE.  The data confirms this: The MSE from the first article is smaller than the second and that the MAE is higher in the first article than the second. Our choice of $f_0$ in each case was, therefore, a good one.

Next, look at the trajectory of the MSE for both models. For $\Delta_m$ trained on residual vectors, the MSE immediately drops by 10x because the regression tree stump for $\Delta_1$ immediately took off after the outlier at $\vec x$=950. The residual from the average to \$2000 rent is so large that the regression tree stump splits the outlier into its own group.  In contrast, the $\Delta_1$ trained on the sign vector splits the observations in between the second and third because the sign vector is $[-1, -1, 0, 1, 1]$. The regression tree chooses to group $[-1, -1]$ together because they are identical values, leaving $[0, 1, 1]$ as the other group. Instead of the magnitude, sign vectors treat anything above the mean as the same value, 1. Here are the $\Delta_1$ predictions again for both composite models:

<table>
<tr>
<th>$\Delta_1$ trained on residual vector
<th>$\Delta_1$ trained on sign vector
<tr>
<td><img src="images/L2-delta1.png" width="70%">
<td><img src="images/L1-delta1.png" width="70%">
</table>

The MSE for weak models trained on the sign vector does not drop dramatically until $\Delta_3$ finally goes after the outlier to yield $F_3$. In fact, the MSE does not budge in between the second and third weak models.  Empirically at least, training $\Delta_m$ on sign vectors does not seem to be optimizing the MSE very well whereas training $\Delta_m$ on residual vectors does optimize MSE well.  In general, we should see the MSE and MAE decrease monotonically but, given the weak approximations of our $\Delta_m$, monotonicity is not guaranteed. The MSE/MAE could bounce around a bit on its way down.

Finally, let's make some observations about the intermediate $\hat{\vec y} = F_m(\vec x)$ model predictions.  The units of each $\hat y$ is rent-dollars, so $\hat{\vec y}$ is a vector of dollar values in $N$-space (here, $N=5$). That means that the $F_m$ predictions are vectors sweeping through $N$-space as we increase $m$.   This is an important concept that we'll rely on below to show GBM is performing gradient descent. When papers use the term "*function space*," they just mean the $N$-space of predictions: a vector of $N$ target values predicted by some $F_m(\vec x)$.


<section title="The intuition behind gradient descent">

Terence and Jeremy both have a story where they had to make their way down a mountain in the pitch black of night or dense fog. (*Spoiler alert*: we both make it back!) Obviously, the way to get down is to keep going downhill until you reach the bottom. More mathematically speaking, we should take steps to the left, right, or at an angle in order to minimize the "elevation function." Rather than trying to find the best angle to step, we can treat each direction forward/backward and left/right separately and then combine them. Swing your foot  forwards and backwards to figure out which way is downhill in that direction then swing your foot left and right to figure out which way is downhill in that direction. If forward and right go downhill, then take a step in the direction of vector $[ forward, right ]$.

what's a gradient?

<img src="images/directions.png" width="30%">

<section title="Boosting as gradient descent in prediction space">

we would choose absolute value difference when we are worried about outliers.

gradient descent does parameter optimization normally but we are now doing function space optimization. Gradient descent can't be doing parameter optimization because the different kinds of models would have different parameters.

The residual vector is the gradient (vector of partial derivatives) of the $L_2$ loss function and the sign vector is the gradient of the $L_1$ loss function. GBMs nudge $\hat{\vec y}$ at each stage in the direction of reduced loss.


\[
\frac{\partial L(y_i, F(\vec x_i))}{\partial F(\vec x_i)}
\]

\[
\frac{\partial L(\vec y, F(X))}{\partial F(X)}
\]

\[
\frac{\partial L(\vec y, \hat{\vec y})}{\partial \hat{\vec y}}
\]

How do you optimize a function? set the derivative to zero and solve for x.
 
Friedman says '*... consider F(x) evaluated at each point $\vec x$ to be a "parameter"*'

<section title="General algorithm">

<latex>
\setlength{\algomargin}{3pt}
\SetAlCapSkip{-10pt}
\SetKwInput{kwReturns}{returns}
\begin{algorithm}[H]
\LinesNumbered
\SetAlgorithmName{Algorithm}{List of Algorithms}
\SetAlgoSkip{}
\SetInd{.5em}{.5em}
\TitleOfAlgo{{\em boost}($X$,$\vec y$,$M$,$\eta$) \kwReturns{model $F_M$}}
Let $F_0(X)$ be value $v$ minimizing $\sum_{i=1}^N L(y_i, v)$, loss across all observations\\
\For{$m$ = 1 \KwTo $M$}{
	Let $\delta_m = \frac{\partial L(\vec y,~ \vec f(X))}{\partial \vec f(X)}\big\rvert_{\vec f=F_{m-1}}$, gradient of $L$ w.r.t. $\vec f$ evaluated at $F_{m-1}$\\
	Train regression tree $\Delta_m$ on $\delta_m$, minimizing squared error\\
	\ForEach{leaf $l \in \Delta_m$}{
		Let $w$ be value minimizing $L(y_i, F_{m-1}(\vec x_i) + w)$ for obs. $i$ in leaf $l$\\
		Alter $l$ to predict $w$ (not the usual $mean(y_i)$)\\
	}
	$F_m(X) = F_{m-1}(X) + \eta \Delta_m(X)$\\
}
\Return{$F_M$}\\
\end{algorithm}
</latex>

<aside title="Why does chasing the sign vector minimize MAE?">

The critical difference is training on the direction only not the magnitude, which gives different groupings. mse makes tree really want to handle the outlier properly. show a single stump where grouping is different radically because the directions make all of the values look the same.
See dev-descent  notebook. I created data that gets radically different trees according to what they're trained on.


<pyeval label="minMAE" output="df" hide=true>
import pandas as pd
import matplotlib.pyplot as plt
from matplotlib import rc
import matplotlib
import numpy as np
from scipy.optimize import minimize_scalar
from sklearn.metrics import mean_squared_error, mean_absolute_error
#rc('text', usetex=True)
matplotlib.rcParams['mathtext.fontset'] = 'cm'
matplotlib.rcParams['mathtext.rm'] = 'serif'
matplotlib.rc('xtick', labelsize=13) 
matplotlib.rc('ytick', labelsize=13) 

bookcolors = {'crimson': '#a50026', 'red': '#d73027', 'redorange': '#f46d43',
              'orange': '#fdae61', 'yellow': '#fee090', 'sky': '#e0f3f8', 
              'babyblue': '#abd9e9', 'lightblue': '#74add1', 'blue': '#4575b4',
              'purple': '#313695'}

df = pd.DataFrame(data={"sqfeet":[700, 750, 800, 850, 900,950,1000]})
df["rent"] = pd.Series([1160, 1160, 1175, 1200, 1280,1310,2000])

M = 1
f0 = df.rent.median()
df['F0'] = f0

for s in range(1,M+1):
    df[f'res{s}'] = df.rent - df[f'F{s-1}']
    df[f'sign{s}'] = np.sign(df[f'res{s}'])
	
df = df.astype(int)
</pyeval>

<pyfig label=minMAE hide=true width="40%">
plt.plot(df.sqfeet,df.rent,'o')

m = df.rent.mean()
mm = np.empty(len(df))
mm.fill(m)
plt.plot(df.sqfeet,mm)

md = df.rent.median()
md2 = np.empty(len(df))
md2.fill(md)
plt.plot(df.sqfeet,md2, linestyle=':')
plt.show()
</pyfig>

Scitkit decision tree gives split point of 975 for training on residual but split of 825 for sign vector. So MSE chases the 800, grouping all others whereas sign vector shows an equal split then takes median. So right leaf for MSE is 800 but is median of 0, 80, 110, 800 = 95. So we aren't taking major steps towards the outlier. First, we're grouping by up/down which ignores magnitude of outlier then we take median which won't let us jump too far towards that. So this is optimizing the abs diff and not giving special emphasis to obs far from median.

modified to have different data. show that mse trajectory is different in L1 than in L2.

```
Opt MSE
RMSE: [322.949  30.557  19.563  17.055  11.956   9.353] (RMSE)
MAE:  [257.2    23.     16.833  13.     11.014   8.035] (RMSE)

MSE drops fast at first when optimizing it. But, doesn't move much at
first when optimizing MAE:

Opt MAE
RMSE: [359.089 336.188 334.606  23.365  22.408  22.792]
MAE:  [183.    163.    161.5    12.25   11.125  10.75 ]

shows opt MAE must be not chasing RMSE.
```

Hmm...maybe we need to do on a bigger data set vaguely linear then add noise and see difference. this is too unstable.


</aside>

<section title="Junk drawer">

Nudging $\hat{\vec y}$ towards target $\vec y$ means nudging $\hat{\vec y}$ in the direction of lower cost, which is "gradient of the loss function," which is where the "gradient" in gradient boosting comes from. Shortly, we'll show that it's also the gradient in gradient descent.

 $\hat{\vec y}$.

Here, again, the $F_m$ predictions are vectors sweeping through dollars $N$-space and the mean absolute error (MAE) falls as we add more weak models. Though it falls more slowly than the MSE, the MAE is also monotonically decreasing. Note that we can drop the "mean" part to get the same the total squared or total absolute error by dropping the $\frac{1}{N}$.

The error measures in both cases never go up because we are specifically choosing to nudge the approximation in the direction of lower cost, which we call the direction vector.  
 
Using the mean by dividing by $N$ is the same as measuring the total squared air or total absolute error because the number of observations is a constant once we start training. It's a constant scalar factor that can be ignored because it doesn't change the shape of the error curve. 

Minimizing some function $f(x)$ will always give the same $x$ as minimizing the same function scaled by constant, $cf(x)$.



Students ask the most natural but hard-to-answer questions:

<ol>
<li>Why is it called *gradient* boosting?
<li>What is "function space"?
<li>Why is it called "gradient descent in function space"?
</ol>

The third question is the hardest to explain. As Gorman points out, "*This is the part that gets butchered by a lot of gradient boosting explanations*." (His blog post does a good job of explaining it, but I thought I would give my own perspective here.)


How good is that model? To answer that, we need a loss or cost function, $L(y,\hat y)$, that computes the cost of predicting $\hat y$ instead of $y$.  The squared error, $L(y,\hat y) = (y-\hat y)^2$ is the most common, but sometimes we care more about the absolute difference, $L(y,\hat y) = |y-\hat y|$. The loss across all observations is just the sum (or the average if you want to divide by $N$) of all the individual observation losses:

\[
L(\vec y, X) = \sum_{i=1}^{N} L(y_i, F_M(\vec x_i))
\]

That gives this either $L(\vec y, X) = \sum_{i=1}^{N} (y_i - F_M(\vec x_i))^2$ or $L(\vec y, X) = \sum_{i=1}^{N} |y_i - F_M(\vec x_i)|$.

Have you ever wondered why this technique is called *gradient* boosting? We're boosting gradients because our weak models learn sign vectors, and the other common term for "direction vector" is, drumroll please, *gradient*.  that leads us to optimization via gradient descent.





only do for trees; then we are just tweaking the predictions in the leaf nodes; use mean of leaf elements already in L2 but tweak to use median in L1 case. Min $L(y_i, F_{m-1}(\vec x_i) + w)$ for $\vec x_i$ in leaf $l$. L2 case, we have $(y_i - F_{m-1}(\vec x_i) - w)^2$ and $y_i - F_{m-1}(\vec x_i)$ is just the residual so $w$ as mean minimizes that. That residual is what we are training on and as we discussed before, the initial value should be either the mean or the median because that minimizes those cost functions.

$\tilde{\vec y} = - \nabla_{F_{m-1}(X)} L(\vec y, F_{m-1}(X))$

= $ \frac{\partial}{\partial F_{m-1}(X)} L(\vec y, F_{m-1}(X))$

$\nabla_{\hat{\vec y}} L(\vec y,\hat{\vec y})$





<section title="Common points of confusion">

picking weights is also an optimization problem.

Conceptually, gradient boosting is pretty easy to explain

Given $(X, \vec y)$ we want an $f(X)$ $f(X_i) = y_i$.

$\vec y = f(X)$

Treating a gradient boosting machine means an initial approximation to the target and then multiple trainings for models that map the x to a nudge.


typical use a gradient boosting is to use a single function that represents the model mapping predictors to target, such as  logistic regression or neural networks. In that case, we are tweaking the models to see how the resulting function output affects the cost function. With gradient boosting, we have multiple functions not just one. Of course when we train each model/function we must do some model-parameter fitting to learn, but that is a totally separate concept.  With gradient boosting, we are not tweaking the parameters of a single function but instead are asking how to tweak the output from a composite function. Each new tweak gets added into the composite function.

Game of golf. hit it once to get it close then nudge, nudge, nudge to get into hole.

$Cost(y, \hat y_0 + \Delta y_1 + \Delta y_2 + ...  + \Delta y_M)$.

$F_0(x) = \hat y$

$F_1(x) = \hat y + \Delta y_1$

$F_2(x) = \hat y + \Delta y_1 + \Delta y_2$

or, instead of nudging along we can try to jump from the initial approximation to the end:

$Cost(y, \hat y + \Delta y)$

The problem is that we can't make the Delta exactly and so we end up with, in both cases,

$Cost(y, \hat y + \hat{\Delta y}_1 + \hat{\Delta y}_2 + ...  + \hat{\Delta y}_M)$.



Want to minimize

$Cost(\vec y, f(X))$

where $f(X)$ is the set of predictions coming from our model $f$. To minimize that, we keep tweaking the parameters of $f$ until we get the minimum cost.  typically we expose those parameters, such as with linear regression model $y = \beta_0 + \beta_1 x$.

$Cost(\vec y, f(X;[\beta_0, \beta_1])$

or

$Cost(\vec y, \beta_0 + \beta_1 x)$

and then say to minimize that equation by shifting $[\beta_0, \beta_1]$ around.
 
$Cost(\vec y, \hat y)$

for some predictions from the model $\hat y$.

The typical iterative update procedure for gradient descent is:

$x_{t+1} = x_t - \eta \nabla f(x_t)$

to find $x$ that minimizes $f(x)$.   When using it to train a model, $x$ is the set of parameters for the model. In neural networks, the architecture is embodied by the $f$ function.

pikes peak metaphor: elevation function is model, x is location. shift x until elevation is minimized.  that is one model  called elevation. x is parameter.  with boosting, get a starting elevation (the summit?) then ask which direction we should take a step to head towards lower elevation at a specific x location.  hmm...maybe it's like we know the elevation at bottom, 6000' (vs 14110' at summit).  We ask, is current elevation 6000? No, need another step so drop elevation by 1 unit. this would be simulating one $\vec x$ and one $y$ target...too easy to move one person downhill. but it's like start at some elevation, now go down until bottom (cost is 0 when we reach bottom). duh. ok, extend so there are 20 kids on trip and all at different starting points. Now pretend they are all at average elevation.  Boosting tweaks not the x location of each kid, but sends a "go down or go up or stop moving signal".   The updated prediction of kid elevations is initial guess of average and then tweaks giving instructions to head up/down to reach same base camp at bottom. (some might have gotten lost and ended up below base camp). Hmm...actually, no. we send park rangers, one per kid, starting at basecamp looking to reach each kid. initial guess basecamp.  Then ask for ranger i, is kid i above/below/same. Tell ranger to move. Ranger elevation is initial + all tweaks. when tweak vector goes to all 0s, rangers have reached all kids. how does x location come into play?  training ranger to move elevation up/down might involve shifting in x/y plane to get single elevation value.

\todo{ To get really fancy, we can even add momentum [Accelerated Gradient Boosting](https://arxiv.org/abs/1803.02042) can mention momentum instead of or in addition to leaf weights.  see accelerated gradient boosting paper recently.}

<section title="Summary">

foo

<aside title="Q. Why is it called >gradient< boosting?">

**A**. We're boosting gradients because the weak models learn direction vectors, and the other common term for "direction vector" is, drumroll please, *gradient*. Yup, simple as that.
</aside>

<section title="Notation translation to Friedman's paper">

foo

<section title="Resources">

Vincent and Bengio [http://www-labs.iro.umontreal.ca/~vincentp/Publications/kmp_mlj.pdf](http://www-labs.iro.umontreal.ca/~vincentp/Publications/kmp_mlj.pdf)

# Junk drawer

The $w_m$ weights are computed by finding the weight that optimizes the mean squared error of the true target $\vec y$ and the proposed $F_m(X)$ model weighted by $w_m$.

The weights, $w_m$, don't appear in the model equations in these graphs because we used weight $w_m = 1$ for simplicity. But, a GBM implementation would choose the optimal weight $w_m$ so as to minimize the squared difference between $\vec y$ and the prediction of the new composite model $F_m(X)$ that used $w_m$. So, first we choose the new weak model $\Delta_m$ then try out different weights, looking for the one that makes best use of this new model.  See page 8 of [Friedman's paper](https://statweb.stanford.edu/~jhf/ftp/trebst.pdf) for the form of the equation (Friedman's equation 12) that, when minimized, yields the appropriate weight for stage $m$. In our notation, the minimization is:

\[
w_m = argmin_w \sum_{i=1}^{N} (y_i - (F_{m-1}(\vec x_i) + w \Delta_m(\vec x_i)))^2
\]

In English, $argmin_w$ just says to find the $w$ such that the value of the summation to the right is minimized. The summation says to compute the loss across all observations between what we want, $y_i$, and what the model would give us if we used weight $w$: $F_{m-1}(\vec x_i) + w \Delta_m(\vec x_i)$.

foo

<!--
Let's perform some manual boosting using this diagram as a guide. Let the target $y$ be 100 yards distant from the tee and the initial approximation, $f_0(\vec x)$, be 70 yards: $F_0(\vec x) = f_0(\vec x) = 70$. The golfer still has $y-70 = 30$ yards to go and so we need to boost the current prediction in the positive direction. Let's use $\Delta_1 (\vec x) = 1$ to indicate a positive delta and, to avoid taking forever, let's scale the new weak learner by $w_1 = 10$: $F_1(\vec x) = 70 + 10$. The golfer is still short so we boost again with $\Delta_2 (\vec x) = 1$ and $w_2 = 10$: $F_2(\vec x) = 70 + 10 + 10$. Finally, we get $\hat y = F_3(\vec x) = 70 + 30 + 30 + 30 = 100$. We would not have to the same  weights, but that is convenient and works for this example. We could also use

 a constant amount

\latex{{
\begin{eqnarray*}
F_0 &=& f_0, ~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~~y-\hat y = 30 \\
F_1 &=& F_0 + 10 \times 1\\
F_2 &=& F_1 + 10 \times 1\\
F_3 &=& F_2 + 10 \times 1\\
\end{eqnarray*}
}}
-->
